A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, United States International Affairs Program (USIAP), Urban Poverty, Office Files of Ghebre Selassie Mehreteab FA664
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, United States International Affairs Program (USIAP), Urban Poverty, Office Files of Ghebre Selassie Mehreteab
1978-1991
Rockefeller Archive Center
Mehreteab, Ghebre Selassie
Ford Foundation
FA664
1.9 Cubic Feet 5 LTR size Hollinger boxes
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011.
A later set of Ghebre Selassie Mehreteab Staff Subject Files was transferred to the RAC in 2019 and ingested by the RAC as Accession 2019:108. This accession was incorporated into the collection during processing in January 2020.
Accessions continue as necessary.
Separated Materials
Appendix A: Reports – Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from their original folders, scanned and transferred to the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports. See Appendix A for a list of these reports and their specific assigned number. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author. The assigned number may be used to access reports in the online catalog.
Arrangement
Collection consists of two series. The correspondence files in the first series are arranged chronologically, and an inconsistent alphabetical arrangement was imposed by the records' creators on the community development corporation grants in the second series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Correspondence files, 1981-1985
Series 2. Community development corporation grants, 1978-1991
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the office files Ghebre Selassie Mehreteab created during his time as a Program Officer in the Ford Foundation's Urban Poverty Program. It consists of two types of files. The first group of files contain Mehreteab's correspondence from the years 1981 to 1985. The second group of files contain Recommended Grant Action records (RGAs) and related materials for the various community development corporations (CDCs) the Urban Poverty Program supported during the 1980s. Mehreteab and his successor Craig Howard oversaw grants concerned with economic development, manpower development, housing, historic preservation, commercial revitalization, political empowerment, community development strategies, and community development information sharing services.
The collection originally consisted only of Mehreteab's correspondence, but another set of Mehreteab's office files was transferred to the RAC in 2019. These files were the CDC RGAs. They were incorporated into the collection as a separate series.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas. During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Biographical / Historical
Ghebre Selassie Mehreteab has been involved in the areas of community development and housing for several decades. From 1981 to 1987, he served as a Program Officer in the Ford Foundation's Urban Poverty Program where he managed grants to community development corporations (CDCs). He cofounded the NHP Foundation in 1989 and served as Chief Executive Officer until 2009.
Mehreteab was born in 1949 in Asmara, Eritrea. He graduated from Haverford College in 1972. Before joining the Ford Foundation, he worked with different community organizations in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania and served as an associate director of the New World Foundation.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Ford Foundation; Community development; Community development corporations; Economic development; Historic preservation; Housing; Low-income housing
- Correspondence files, 1981-1985; 1; .19 Cubic Feet About .5 LTR size Hollinger box
  Scope and Contents
  Series contains the correspondence Ghebre Selassie Mehreteab created during his time as a Program Officer in the Ford Foundation's Urban Poverty Program. The correspondence discusses community economic development grant requests, grant recommendations, current grantees, site visits to grantees, trips, and meeting s. A number of documents concern the community development corporation (CDC) training workshops the Ford Foundation organized. Mehreteab chiefly corresponded with grantees and potential grantees, Urban Poverty Program Officer in Charge Bernard McDonald and other Ford Foundation staff members, and other individuals involved with community economic development.
  The material in the series was created between 1981 and 1985. The series does not include Mehreteab's correspondence from his last years at the Ford Foundation.
  - Correspondence file, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence file, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence file, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence file, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Community development corporation grants, 1978-1991; 2; 1.71 Cubic Feet About 4.5 LTR size Hollinger boxes
  Files in the series chiefly consist of Recommended Grant Action records (RGAs) for the various community development corporations (CDCs) and other organizations involved with community economic development that the Ford Foundation supported during the 1980s. Some files include correspondence, memos, reports, and other types of materials in addition to a RGA or RGAs. There are some reports about the Foundation's support for CDCs at the beginning of the series as well as a file filled with program action forms and grant recommendations at the end of the series. The CDCs and other organizations that the Foundation supported pursued projects and initiatives related to economic development, manpower development, housing, historic preservation, commercial revitalization, political empowerment, community development strategies, and community development information sharing services.
  The series contains RGAs for the CDC grants Ghebre Selassie Mehreteab managed but also RGAs for the grants that Mehreteab's successor Craig Howard oversaw.
  - Support for Emerging Community Development Corporations, 1983 March (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Urban Poverty Program Request for Proposal - Community development corporations, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Corrective Capitalism: The Rise of America's Community Development Corporations, 1987 July (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Research Foundation of the City University of New York, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Association of Neighborhood Housing Developers, Inc., 1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Arkansas Institute for Social Justice, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - The Allegheny West Foundation/San Jose Development Corporation, 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Allegheny Conference on Community Development, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Center for Southeast Asian Refugee Resettlement, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Central Germantown Council, 1983-1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Community Information Exchange, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Community Development Corporation of Boston, 1984-1988 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Citizens Forum for Self-Government (see National Municipal League), 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Drew Economic Development Corporation, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Denver Indian Center Development Corporation, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Corporation for Public/Private Ventures, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - East Little Havana Community Development Corporation, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - East Liberty Development, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Institute for Community Economics, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Kenilworth Courts/Parkside Addition Resident Management Company, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - East St. Louis Community Foundation, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Enterprise Foundation, 1982-1989 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - East Bay Asian Local Development Corporation, 1978-1989 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - GLIE Community Youth Program, Inc., 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Greenmount Development, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Haitian Task Force, 1984-1988 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Homewood-Brushton Revitalization and Development Corporation, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Hunting Park Community Development Corporation, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Institute for Community Economics, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Local Initiatives Support Corporation (LISC), 1989-1991 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Low Income Housing Information Service, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Manchester Citizens Corporation, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Marshall Heights Community Development Organization, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Minority Business Information Institute, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Minority Developer Assistance Corporation, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - National Center for Policy Alternatives, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - National Council for Urban Economic Development, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - National Economic Association, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - National Federation of Community Development Credit Unions, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) Legal Defense and Education Fund (LDF), 1988 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - National Municipal League, Inc., 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - National Neighborhood Coalition, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - National Temple Non Profit Corporation, 1984-1987 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - National Urban Coalition, 1982-1987 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Neighborhood Institute, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - National Trust for Historic Preservation, 1981-1985 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - North Side Civic Development Council, Inc., 1983-1987 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Northside Preservation Commission, 1983-1988 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Northeast Community Development Corporation, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Newark Collaboration Group, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - NEWSED Community Development Corporation, 1983-1988 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Northeast Denver Housing Center, Inc., 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - New Hampshire College, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Oakland Planning and Development Corporation, 1983-1986 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Operation Life Community Development Corporation, 1984-1988 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Opportunities Industrialization Center (OIC) of Rhode Island, Inc., 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Opportunities Industrialization Center (OIC) of Rhode Island, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Opportunities Resource Institute (ORI), 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Partnerships Data Net, 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Park Heights Development Corporation, 1983-1986 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Progress of Peoples Development Corporation, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Piton Community Development Project, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Task Force for Historic Preservation and the Minority Community, 1984-1988 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Philadelphia Fund for Community Development, 1986-1989 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Philadelphia Cooperation Office, 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Pratt Institute, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Structured Employment/Economic Development Corporation (SEEDCO), 1986-1989 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Society for the Preservation of Weeksville and Bedford Stuyvesant History, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - University of Texas, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Urban Affairs Partnership, 1984-1987 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Tacolcy Economic Development Corporation, Inc., 1983-1989 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - West Oak Lane Community Development Corporation, 1984-1986 (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Woodstock Institute, 1987-1989 (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Community development grant program action forms and recommendations, 1985-1987 (Box 5, Folder 78-79)